Hello, I'm Yasodara Cordova

+1 857 265 4068
Public Bio (Wikipedia Article): https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasodara_Cordova Twitter, Medium, Github: @yaso ydamocordova@worldbank.org

Objectives

I am a technologist with a background in design, software development, working with public policies & technology to foster sustainable development. Currently, I work as an AGILE/Civic Tech Fellow at the World Bank, and my mandate is to connect Agile with Civic Tech, and Digital Development with Democratic innovation. In the past, I've worked with innovation in Digital Government at the digital HKS, a program at the Belfer Center at the Harvard Kennedy School. I was also an affiliate of the Berkman Klein Center for Internet & Society at Harvard, a position that I have had since I was selected to be a Fellow of the Center during the academic year of 2016-17. In 2016 I was also CEO of an AI & Anti-corruption project featuring a robot, called Rosie. I successfully developed a business strategy for the project's sustainability. Previously, I worked as a Web specialist for the World Wide Web Consortium, leading the development of technical standards for the Web. Before that, I worked as a Technical Consultant at the United Nations Program for Development, where I developed the platform for the most significant public participation experiment via the Internet in Brazil, the public consultation platform for the "Marco Civil da Internet do Brasil," and several other public participation platforms for the Brazilian Federal Government.

Working Experience

WorldBank Group, Agile/civic tech - Fellow (July 2019 - present)

- Co-developed a strategy and gave expert support for Mozambique's Digital Response to the COVID-19 crisis.
- Advised various central and country teams on how to create digital platforms for citizen participation.
- Advised Smart Cities and Civic Tech project development in Angola and Kazakhstan, focusing on products for data and public policies.
- Advised teams from Malaysia, Tanzania, Brazil on how to build and deploy technologies for citizen engagement, institutional data collection & dataset integration for Digital Government transformation.
- Co-led a team in the delivery of the Diagnostic on Digital Development (DE4A) in Angola, resulting in a report on public digital platforms for the country.
- With the GovTech, produced guidelines on financial systems management and technologies for data and fraud detection in the Public Sector.
- Worked on Public Policies for Artificial Intelligence implementation, including strategy and production of digital public platforms in Developing Countries.
- Delivered Agile methodologies and tools training for various Bank's country teams and client countries' teams.

digitalHKS, Belfer Center, Harvard University - Senior Fellow (July 2018 - June 2019)

- In partnership with the New York Times, co-led a team of researchers to investigate YouTube's impact on Brazil's elections. Research results were featured in The New York Times and other press outlets, and one short-documentary.
- In partnership with Facebook and the Shorenstein Center, developed a solution for automation of bulk messages on WhatsApp in the context of the Comprova project, from the First Draft organization.
- Trained journalists on the use of connected platforms developed to share information on the main issues affecting the Brazilian presidential campaign.
- Assisted the Center's Associate Director on grant writing.
- Lead research and publication on data and inequality.
- Organized the workshops "Big Data, Meager returns" (2018) and "Data as Development" (2019), both sponsored and hosted by the Kennedy School

digitalHKS, Belfer Center, Harvard University - *Fellow* (July 2017 - June 2018)

- Published/Produced research on social media and bots, focusing on the potential effects of issuing service identities to robots on social media
- Conducted and evaluated research about Identity, citizenship, cloud communities, blockchain, and sovereignty of indigenous communities' digital identity systems in place in Brazil
- Organized workshops about "Blockchain for Public Policies" in Brazil (year)
- Spoke in several conferences including the 'International Dialogues on Technology, Regulation, and Public Policies", (Brazil 2017).

Berkman Klein Center for Internet and Society, Harvard University

Affiliate August 2017 - June 2019
Fellow - September 2016 - August 2017

- Delivered documents and reports related to programs, conferences, and seminars.
- Conducted forecasting to determine possible changes and issues for the implementation of Digital Identity, Citizenship, and Democracy in Brazil.
- Collaborated with the center's professionals to advance research and gain a deeper understanding of topics surrounding privacy, digital identity, web architecture, and laws and regulations.
- Organized the workshop "Algorithms, Law, and Society: Building Rights for a Digital Era," 2016, at the Harvard Law School.

Serenata de Amor Operation - *Chief Executive Officer* (September 2017 - August 2018)

- Led a team that developed an open data Artificial Intelligence platform focused on accountability of the Brazilian Congress. Managed the project to its growth, organizing the team in person and remotely.
- Determined the project's vision and strategic direction, also in support of fundraising, and coordinating resources to achieve the goals within optimal timeframes and limited (financial and human) resources.
- Managed partnerships and strategic business relationships, including negotiating contract terms and handling conflicts.
- Prepared organization for forecasted demand levels through effective operational planning.

- Orchestrated positive media coverage and stakeholder relations as the public face of the Serenata de Amor Operation, and presented the project at the Brazilian Congress, Harvard, and MIT.
- Coached and guided senior developers to improve effectiveness and feature delivery, resulting in higher performance levels
- Negotiated the terms of sustainability for the project, including incorporation by the Open Knowledge Foundation.

Avaaz - *Technical Consultant for Encrypted Chat apps* (April 2018 - August 2018)

- Provided high-level technical expertise to projects in the area of encrypted chat apps and online disinformation for advocacy and policy-making processes
- Delivered in-depth cryptography training to the company's team, imparting knowledge of best practices for informing legislative processes

The Center for Technology & Society (CTS), FGV School of Law - Fellow

- Featured articles about APIs and open data for smart cities and public policies versus citizen's privacy
- Analyzed data to build parameters for further research at the institution, about Smart Cities and Inequality
- Conducted and evaluated research using cutting edge technology, including data collection, structure, and analysis, on Facebook's social media data and public policies

World Wide Web Consortium, Brazil

Project Manager, Web Specialist – May 2013 - July 2016 *Developer Relations* – May 2012 - May 2013

- Led the development of standards for the web as the first Brazilian chairing a W3C
 Working Group, guiding the Working Group to the development of the Data on the Web Best Practices standards
- Contributed in the Web Payments Industry, Working Group, and the Linked Data Working Group
- Fostered the Brazilian participation at the W3C consortium advocating for the use of Open Web Standards, increasing the number of Latin American participants in 60%
- Delivered several talks, nationally and Internationally, about Web APIs, Semantic Web, Linked Data, Privacy, Web Payments, Data on the Web, and correlated issues.
- Organized several workshops, conferences, and events with business partners
- Managed multiple projects that aimed to innovate the use of the Web in Brazil
- Conducted the development and implementation of the consortium partnerships, as, the collaboration with the Brazilian Ministry of Justice, aiming at analyzing data from public participation to support platforms of direct law-making processes
- Led the process of translation for several standards and documentation, produced research related to the web, presenting in academic conferences, like the ISWC2015 and the 2015 Open Data Research Symposium

UNited Nations - Technical consultant

Presidency of the Republic, Brazil – Jan 2012 - May 2012

Ministry of Justice, Brazil – Oct 2010 - Oct 2011

Ministry of Culture, Brazil – Jan 2010 - Oct 2010

- Developed platform prototypes for the interaction between the citizen and the Presidency Youth Secretariat
- Consulted with product development teams to enhance the development of the public social media prototypes based on socio economic data
- Delivered the first version of the public social media platform called "Participatório da Juventude", (or Youth's participatory)
- Managed benchmarks, prototype demonstrations and texts for the development of public participation and digital democracy processes
- Developed the UX/UI for the platform of the Ministry of Justice for public consultation of bills proposed by the Secretariat for Legislative Affairs, the "Pensando o Direito"
- Advised on the creation and deployment of platforms for public participation in law making processes
- Applied future forecasting techniques to develop proposals for the distribution and integration of digital libraries in Brazil
- Advised on the strategies for improving the public access to cultural production, supporting open source software development on the government
- Developed a prototype for a platform for the public participation in Brazilian law-making processes
- Chaired weekly meetings with legislative leadership to identify opportunities for improvement and establish milestones for the platform used to consult with the citizen

Brazilian Communication Company, Brazil *Project Manager, UX lead* (Aug 2008 - Jan 2010)

- Maintained tactical control of project budgets and timelines to keep teams on-task and achieve schedule targets
- Oversaw a large portfolio of projects to support multimedia journalism and public communications
- Practiced lean principles, which led to improvements in workflow and innovation in platforms used for multimedia distribution
- Established and oversaw synchronized, cohesive team by inspiring confidence and offering guidance to the developers and designers
- Oversaw projects for journalism by planning, designing, iterating and scheduling the development cycles
- Outlined work plans, determining resources, wrote timelines, and generated initial budgets as part of project scope decisions.
- I implemented agile methods to develop software and was the agile coach of the team.
- Coordinated a team of designers, developers, and journalists producing data visualization and special multimedia projects
- Implemented Agile Methods, usability and accessibility tests for all our products, which increased the production by 40%
- The team delivered a low-cost solution that worked for the reports of the two subsequent Brazilian elections.
- Designed animations, illustrations, and data visualization
- Designed the UX and UX for the multimedia pieces that won the Vladimir Herzog award for Human Rights twice in a row (2008 and 2009)

Radiobras, Brazil – UX Designer (Feb 2007 - Jan 2009)

- Implemented several new tools and features in the news platform used at the public news online agency.
- Designed the user experience and engineered the front end of various data visualization and multimedia journalism pieces

- Designer of multimedia storytelling that won the Vladimir Herzog award for Journalism and Human Rights in 2008. The multimedia piece was about the Communities of Quilombolas (the Brazilian that are descendants of enslaved Africans)
- Implemented open-source technologies to automate the new Web Portal of the Brazilian public news agency (Agência Brasil), supporting the Creative Commons Licences and participatory journalism.

Redecomm, Brazil - *Innovation Consultant* (Jan 2006 - Jan 2007)

• Developed the company's strategic planning, using Agile methodologies. The company won an entrepreneurship Prize given by The University of Brasilia in 2006.

Advisory board positions

- Advisors Board, Affirmative Action for Algorithms Women@TheTable (2019 -)
- Directors Board, Cidadania Inteligente (2019 -)
- Calango Hackerspace (Founder, 2012. Advisor 2014-)
- Former Advisors Board, Coding Rights (2015-2017)
- Audit Committee & Board member, Open Knowledge Foundation (2014-2017)

Teaching Experience

- Lecturer | International School of Governance, CGI.br, Brazil 2014 2015.
- Guest Lecturer | IDP Brazil Law Institute, Brasil | Internet Lab, Brazil 2009 2011.
- Substitute Prof | Federal University of Brasilia | Universidades Paulista-UNIP 2009- 2011
- Guest Lecturer | Internet Lab, Brazil 2017
- Lecturer | Fatec Technical Public School of Sao Paulo, Brazil 2015
- Online Instructor | TimTec Platform, Brazil 2015

Education

- Fundação Getulio Vargas, Brasilia | MBA Strategic Marketing Management Class of 2007
- Universidade Federal de Brasília (UnB) | Bachelor, Industrial Design Class of 2005

Talks and Media

Source List Profile: Yasodara Cordova

- 2020: Civic Tech, Tax, and Trust | TicTec Online Conference
- 2019: Panelist, GPSA Forum "Addressing Constraints to Social Accountability for Inclusion"
- 2019 Panelist, Spring Meetings panelist "GovTech: Putting People First" (video available)
- 2018: Emerging Technologies and Global Citizenship Workshop Indigenous Cloud Communities
- 2017: Digital HKS School Lunch Seminar Architecture for Al transparency: the Serenata de Amor Operation
- 2017 MIT Media Lab, AI ideas exchange: Architecture for AI transparency: the Serenata de Amor Operation
- 2017 ENAP/Kennedy School, International Dialogues on Technology, Regulation and Public Policies
- 2017 Brazilian Congress, Artificial Intelligence for transparency and accountability

- 2017 FGV School, Fintechs and Regulation for Innovation
- 2017 Internet Lab, Cryptocurrencies and the Decentralized Future
- 2017 Olabi Makerspace, Cryptocurrencies, and Regulation
- 2015 International Open Data Conference, Open Data Standards: Good Practices
- 2015 Condatos, Como Mejorar la oferta de Datos Publicos?
- 2015 Condatos, Standares y datos abiertos como intermediarios
- 2015 keynote Tropical Ruby 2015, 25 Minutes of Semantic Web
- 2015 International Free Software Forum Do you have time to listen to the Word of the Web
- 2018 Business Daily by BBC Podknife: On Data and Misinformation
- 2013 InfoQ HTML APIs: Frameworks for the Future
- 2012 Ossobuco Hackerspaces in Brazil

Sample of latest publications

2019:

<u>Latin America Hopes Big Data Can Beat the Virus. But There Are Risks.</u> Americas Quarterly. Yasodara Cordova & Beatriz Botero

<u>Digital government in developing countries</u>, Book Chapter. Yasodara Cordova & Tiago Peixoto.

<u>Rosie the Robot: Social accountability one tweet at a time</u>. World Bank Blogs, Yasodara Cordova & Eduardo Goncalves

Awards

2020: Fellow, Portulans Institute

2017: Frida Prize, Internet, and Human Rights

2012: "A Rede" Prize for Public Policies, Collaboration Platforms

2009 & 2008: Vladimir Herzog for Human Rights and Journalism, <u>Internet and Multimedia</u>

Languages

Portuguese - Native | English - Proficiency | French - basic reading & conversation | Spanish

Skills

Agile methods | Git, Bash, basic coding skills | UX Design | Business Intelligence | Web Architecture | Strategy